- [Instructor] Hello everyone.
In this lesson I'm going to explain
what is node.js, and we're going to install it.
But first let's review the client-server model.
In a typical web app there are two parts,
the server and the client.
The server is the central part
that executes the most important tasks.
On the other hand, the clients are the people or devices
that your use your app through a browser.
For example, the client can be running
from a computer or from a smart phone
or from multiple computers at the same time.
The client can also execute code.
For example, you can add some JavaScript code
to be used by the client.
For example, maybe you have already down that;
used JavaScript to create interactive websites
in the client site.
The idea of node.js is different.
Node.js is an engine that allows you to write
server-site code using JavaScript.
So, Node.js will run inside a server
but you can execute code using it
and this code will be in JavaScript.
The idea is that you write your JavaScript code,
and the engine executes the code in the server.
Now let's install it.
First, open the Node website like I've done here.
Here you can load a version of the engine
for our operation system.
I'm using Windows.
So I will download an installer for it.
If you're using Linux or Mac,
you can download a pre-compiled binary.
There are two options, the LTS here.
This is recommended for most users
and is the most stable version.
This is the version we are going to use in this course.
And we also have the Current version,
which is the most recent one.
It has the newest features,
but it might have some bugs,
so we are going to stick to the LTS version.
I've already installed the Node.js engine in my computer,
so I'm not going to do it again.
But if you don't have it installed in your computer,
so please pause the video now,
download the version for your operation system,
and install it.
After you install it you can test it
if it's working correctly by running it.
If you're using Linux or Mac,
you can go to the binary folder,
you have downloaded from the site,
and just execute the binary in the terminal.
You can also execute it through the Windows terminal,
and that's what you're going to do to here.
So, open here, and we can run, for example, Node.
This should execute the Node engine.
However, the Windows terminal, it doesn't support
Unix-like command lines.
At the time of this recording,
it has been announced a new batch terminal for Windows.
But in the meantime,
you can download a free git batch terminal,
for example, this one.
You can access gitforwindows.org
and download a git batch terminal.
So it provides you a terminal with Unix-like commands.
You can see it should look like this.
And then here you can use Unix-like commands lines.
Lines here.
And you can also use git commands.
But in this course,
I'm going to use the full Windows terminal,
but you can use the one you prefer.
As you can see, here I'm running the Node engine.
And after running it,
you can run any JavaScript code.
For example, let's create "hello world" messages.
Here it is, hello world.
So it's working.
Now we know it's working,
but in the real world,
we want to write our JavaScript code in a separate file,
and not right in here inside of the engine itself.
And that's what you're going to do in the next lesson.
Where we are going to create out Hello World using Node,
but adding the Hello World in a separate JavaScript file.